Guide to the James Laughton Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
James Laughton Papers
1920-1955
RG 190
Yale University Divinity School Library
2.5
(5 boxes)
Letters, writings, and collected material document the life and work of James Fyfe Laughton. Laughton was born of missionary parents in China, returning to Scotland to continue his education. He later studied at Crozer Seminary in Chester, PA, was ordained to the Baptist ministry in 1912, and served as pastor of a church in Westport, New York for seven years. In 1920 he was called by the American Baptist Foreign Mission Society to direct the work of their mission ship "Fukuin Maru" sailing among the islands of the Inland Sea and coast of Japan. He returned to America in 1926, traveled widely, and was engaged in religious education, lecturing, writing, and pastoral work.
Laughton, James Fyfe
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
James Fyfe Laughton was born in northwest China, son of Scottish Presbyterian missionary parents. He attended the Quaker Mission School for missionary children in Chungking. He went to Scotland for further study and attended various academies, and the Technical Naval College in Greenock. He was in the British Naval Service but resigned to become a missionary. Feeling the need for further study, he went to the U.S. in 1910 and attended Crozer Theological Seminary in Chester, Pennsylvania. He was ordained as a Baptist minister in 1912 and served as pastor of the First Baptist Church, Westport, New York for seven years. In 1920 he was called by the American Baptist Foreign Mission Society to captain their mission ship "Fukuin Maru" sailing among the islands of the Inland Sea and coast of Japan.
Laughton returned to the U.S. in 1926 after the work of the "Fukuin Maru" was turned over to the Japanese, traveling widely on the way. The next few years were spent lecturing before various church and community groups and teaching. In 1929-1930 he served as Associate and Executive Secretary of Religous Education in the state of Maine. He was then called to become the pastor of the Woodhaven Baptist Church, Queens, New York, where he served for ten years. He traveled to Germany in 1934 to study the political, religious, and social conditions there. He served as chaplain for various ocean cruise lines during the 1930s.
Laughton was a lecturer at the International Seminary, East Orange, New Jersey prior to his call to the First Congregational Church, Ticonderoga, New York in 1941. He later served the Rugby Congregational Church in Brooklyn, NY and the Prospect Heights Presbyterian Church in Brooklyn, NY. He had a particular interest in inter-racial and inter-creedal groups. Laughton also was a writer, columnist, and cartoonist for various newspapers. He died in June, 1962.
Scope and Contents
Laughton's eclectic career as a missionary, minister, lecturer, and writer is documented sporadically in this small collection. Of particular interest are the materials related to Laughton's work on the "Fukuin Maru" mission ship in Japan between 1920 and 1926.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence
II. Writings
III. Collected Material
IV. Biographical Material
V. Addendum - 2010
Missions -- Japan; Missionaries; Laughton, James Fyfe; American Baptist Foreign Mission Society
- Correspondence, Series I
  - Family
    - Letters to his wife, 1942,1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Other Letters
    - Samples of testimonials on 25th anniversary of ordination, 1937 Feb (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters of reference - testimonials, 1949, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1931-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letters on leaving Westport NY Church, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Re. ministry - Maine Council of Religious Education, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Re. ministry - Woodhaven Baptist Church, 1931, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Recommendations re- chaplaincy - US Reserves, 1941, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Re. ministry - 1st Congregation Church - Ticonderoga, 1941, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Re. ministry - Rugby Church - Brooklyn, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Advocacy letters for people in military, 1946-1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Advocacy letters for refugees, 1949, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Writings, n.d.; Series II
  - "The Romance of the Jews", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Re. parents' mission experience in China, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Is there memory in heaven?", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - '"A Voice by the Wayside" - Columns - including "Don't be in a hurry"; "Can you take it"; "Servants"; " Confidence"; etc. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "The Pulpit Speaks" - collection (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sermons A - F: including "Andrew - the first Christian worker"; "The Church and the Hour"; "Facing Life" (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sermons G - H: including "Getting together"; "The Gospel and our world"; " How it all began" (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Sermons I - J: including "Immortality and Nature"; "Is a Cross Necessary?"; "Is there a future for religion?" (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sermons K - N: including "Keeping Out of the Fog"; "Love and Learn"; "New Life" (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Sermons O - Q: "Outside and Inside"; "Pentecost"; "Pioneering With Christ" (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Sermons R - W: "Ready-made Clothes"; "Seeing Things"; "Self-Starters"; "The Weakness of Christianity" (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Sermons - Untitled (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Bible Studies: including "Who is God"; "The First Age" (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Lectures: including "Personal Work and Pastoral Visitation"; "Your Aim in Life" (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "The Gospel in Symbols"; "A Dollar Speaks" (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Certificate of Baptism, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Sermon Fragments (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Collected Material, Series III
  - Woodhaven Baptist Church - Youth group material, "Who is Who" "The Assistant Pastor" plus Rugby Church News (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Publications re- Unamerican Activities (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Booklets - "The Christian Commitment"; "Gleanings" (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Micellaneous items (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Brotherhood activities - interaction with Jewish community (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Photographs: Laughtons (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Photographs: Others; Buildings (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Photographs: Baptismal water from Jordan River (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Photo album - Scotland, Japan (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Ship's Logs - "Fukuin Maru" - Japan and "Resolute" (Cruise Ship) (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Masonic Movement (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Notes and Quotes (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - News Clippings (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Scrap Book, 1925-1930 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Scrap Book (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Biographical Information, Series IV
  - Certificates, statements, booklets (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Addendum - 2010, Series V
  - Letter from JFL's wife Elizabeth (Walker) to her family; Christmas greeting card with photo of JFL, ca. 1940s (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Letter copybook of Elizabeth Walker (Laughton), with enclosures, 1907-1911 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Legal documents related to family of Elizabeth Walker (Laughton), 1892 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photograph of Fukuin Maru ship anchored in Inland Sea, Japan; ribbon with "Fukuin Maru" printed on it, 1926, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Glass lantern slides from Japan, ca. 1920s (Box OV1)
  - American flag flown on the Fukuin Maru 1921-1923, 1920s (Box OV1)
  - Framed photograph of crew of mission ship Fukuin Maru 1922-1926 with Mr. and Mrs. Laughton, ca. 1926 (Box OV2)
  - Mounted photograph of Fukuin Maru in the Japan Inland Sea, ca. 1920s (Box OV2)